<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- 

CHANGES:

170611(df):

Modifications from meeting, RS, RR 17/06/11 @clara

- Rewrote section "On the use of STATE and DUMP TLVs"
- Renamed ADS to ADM (since ASM would be ASS)
- Added ASM (and added extra to "On the use of ADVISE TLVs")
- Changed all occurrences of "peer" to "neighbor" in standards language (i.e not in use cases)
- Added BUSY NS Subcode
- Added to sec considerations
- Implemented YMBK BGP Max Size
- Implemented NS "Not Found"
- Implemented SSQ/SSP
- Implemented multifaceting of PRI
- Changed "Not Supported" to "Not Satisfied"

040611(df):

Modifications from RR:

- Changed title to "draft-frs-bgp-operational-message" 
- Changed order of authors to alphabetical
- Updated Date
- Changed Status to "Standards Track" (info->std)
- Changed ADS payload from ASCII to UTF-8
- Changed descriptions of LPCQ and LPCP to indicate "BGP" (Loc-Rib)
- Changed format of PRI to refer to NLRI documentation
- Changed Acknowledgements (Merged diagnostic acks)
- Removed "Not Allowed" and "Not Available", replaced with "Not Supported" and "Max Permitted"


290511(df): 

- Removed reference to flags from capability
- Removed all references to proxying

260511(df): Minutes from Call

Agreed the following types:

  Type 1 - Advisory String

  Type 2 - Number of Reachable Prefixes Transmitted/Received
  Type 3 - Number of prefixes in BGP_RIB_Out
  Type 4 - Number of prefixes present in BGP_RIB

  Type 5 - Prefixes present in dropped attribute message
  Type 6 - Prefixes present in malformed attribute message
  Type 7 - Entire malformed update message enclosure

  Type 8 - Prefix specific BGP query
  Type 9 - Prefix specific BGP response

  Type 10 - BGP attribute specific prefix query
  Type 11 - BGP attribute specific prefix response

...
  
  Type 65534 - "Not Allowed" Response
  Type 65535 - "Not Available" Response

Agreed that types 5 and 6 will be structured using reach/unreach and will be per AFI/SAFI

Agreed that response types of "Not Allowed" and "Not Available" will be 
defined using reserved values.



-->


<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC1997 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1997.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2629 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3640 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3640.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4271 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4360 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4360.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4760 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4760.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4893 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4893.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5492 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5492.xml">
<!ENTITY draft-jasinska-ix-bgp-route-server-02 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.jasinska-ix-bgp-route-server.xml">
<!ENTITY draft-ietf-idr-advisory-00 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-advisory.xml">
<!ENTITY draft-raszuk-bgp-diagnostic-message-02 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.raszuk-bgp-diagnostic-message.xml">
<!ENTITY draft-shakir-idr-ops-reqs-for-bgp-error-handling-01 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.shakir-idr-ops-reqs-for-bgp-error-handling.xml">
<!ENTITY draft-retana-bgp-security-state-diagnostic-00 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.retana-bgp-security-state-diagnostic.xml">
<!ENTITY draft-nalawade-bgp-soft-notify-01 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.nalawade-bgp-soft-notify.xml">
<!ENTITY draft-nalawade-bgp-inform-02 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.nalawade-bgp-inform.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-frs-bgp-operational-message-00">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="bgp-operational-message">
    	 	    BGP OPERATIONAL Message
                 </title>
		<author initials="D." surname="Freedman" fullname="David Freedman">
			<organization abbrev="Claranet">
                        Claranet
                    </organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street/>
					<city>London</city>
					<country>UK</country>
				</postal>
				<email>david.freedman@uk.clara.net</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="R" surname="Raszuk" fullname="Robert Raszuk">
			<organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
					<city>San Jose</city>
					<region>CA</region>
					<code>95134</code>
					<country>US</country>
				</postal>
				<email>raszuk@cisco.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials = 'R.' surname='Shakir' fullname='Rob Shakir'>
            <organization abbrev='C&amp;W'>
                Cable&amp;Wireless Worldwide
            </organization>
            <address>
		<postal>
			<street/>
			<city>London</city>
			<country>UK</country>
		</postal>
                <email>rjs@cw.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>
		<date month="June" year="2011"/>
		<area>Routing</area>
		<workgroup>IDR Working Group</workgroup>
		<keyword>I-D</keyword>
		<keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
		<keyword>IDR</keyword>
		<keyword>BGP</keyword>
		<keyword>OPERATIONAL</keyword>
		<keyword>ADVISORY</keyword>
		<keyword>DIAGNOSTIC</keyword>
		<abstract>
			<t>
				The BGP Version 4 routing protocol (RFC4271) is now used in many ways, crossing boundaries of administrative and technical 
				responsibility. 
			</t>
			<t>
				The protocol lacks an operational messaging plane which could be utilised to diagnose, troubleshoot and inform upon
				various conditions across these boundaries, securely, during protocol operation, without disruption. 
			</t>
			<t>
				This document proposes a new BGP message type, the OPERATIONAL message, which can be used to effect such a messaging plane for 
				use both between and within Autonomous Systems.
			</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>
		<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
			<t>	
				In this document, a new BGP message type, the OPERATIONAL message is defined, creating a communication channel over which messages
				can be passed, using a series of contained TLV elements. 
			</t>
			<t> 
				The messages can be human readable, for the attention of device operators or machine readable, in order to provide simple self test routines,
				which can be exchanged between BGP speakers.
			</t>
			<t>
				A number of TLV elements will be assigned to provide for these message types, along with TLV elements to assist with description of the message data, 
				such as describing precisely BGP prefixes and encapsulating BGP UPDATE messages to be sent back for inspection in order to troubleshoot
				session malfunctions. 
			</t>
			<t>
				The use of OPERATIONAL messages will be negotiated by BGP Capability <xref target="RFC5492"/>, since the messages are in-band with the BGP
				session, they can be assumed to either be authenticated as originating directly from the BGP neighbor. 
			</t>
			<t>
				The goal of this document is to provide a simple, extensible framework within which new messaging and diagnostic requirements can live.
			</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Applications">

			<t> 
				The authors would like to propose three main applications which BGP OPERATIONAL TLVs are designed to address. 
				New TLVs can be easily added to enhance further current applications or to propose new applications.
			</t>
			
			<t>The set of TLVs is organised in the following four functional groups comprising the three applications and some control messaging:</t>
			
			<t>
				<list style="symbols">
					<t> 
						ADVISE TLVs, designed to convey human readable information to be passed, cross boundary to operators, to inform them of past or upcoming
						error conditions, or provide other relevant, in-band operational information. The "Advisory Demand Message" 
						ADM (<xref target="advisory-demand-message"/>) is an example of this. 
					</t>
					<t>
						STATE TLVs, designed to carry information about BGP state across BGP neighbors, including both per-neighbor and global counters. 
					</t>
					
					<t>
						DUMP TLVs, designed to describe or encapsulate data to assist in realtime or post-mortem diagnostics, such as structured representations
						of affected prefixes / NLRI and encapsulated raw UPDATE messages for inspection.
					</t>
					
					<t>
						CONTROL TLVs, designed to facilitate control messaging such as replies to requests which can not be satisfied.
					</t>
					
				</list>
		</t>
		
		<t> 
			Means concerning the reporting of information carried by these TLVs, either in reply or request processing 
			are implementation specific but could include methods such as SYSLOG.
		</t>
			
			
		</section>
		<section anchor="bgp-operational-message" title="BGP OPERATIONAL message">
			<section anchor="capability" title="BGP OPERATIONAL message capability">
				<t>
					A BGP speaker that is willing to exchange BGP OPERATIONAL Messages with a neighbor should advertise the 
					new OPERATIONAL Message Capability to the neighbor using BGP Capabilities advertisement <xref target="RFC5492"/> . 
					A BGP speaker may send an OPERATIONAL message to its neighbor only if it has received the OPERATIONAL message 
					capability from them.
				</t>

				<t>
					The Capability Code for this capability is specified in the IANA
					Considerations section of this document.
				</t>

				<t>The Capability Length field of this capability is 2 octets. 
				</t>

				<figure title='OPERATIONAL message BGP Capability Format'>
				<preamble></preamble>
				<artwork align='center'>

+------------------------------+
| Capability Code (1 octet)    |
+------------------------------+
| Capability Length (1 octet)  |
+------------------------------+


				</artwork>
				<postamble>
				</postamble>
				</figure>

			</section>
			<section anchor="encoding" title="BGP OPERATIONAL message encoding">
				
				<t>
					The BGP message as defined <xref target="RFC4271"/> consists of a fixed-size header followed by two octet length field and one octet of type value. 
					The RFC limits the maximum message size to 4096 octets. As one of the applications of BGP OPERATIONAL message (through the MUD 
					(<xref target="malformed-update-dump"/>) message) is to be able to carry an entire, potentially malformed BGP UPDATE, this specification mandates 
					that when the neighbor has negotiated the BGP OPERATIONAL message capability, any further BGP message which may be subject enclosure 
					within a BGP OPERATIONAL message must be sent with the maximum size reduced to accommodate for the potential need of additional wrapping header 
					size requirements. This is applicable to both the current BGP maximum message size limit or for any future modifications.
				</t>

				<t>
					For the purpose of the OPERATIONAL message information encoding we will use one or more Type-Length-Value containers where each TLV will have the following format:</t>

				<figure title='OPERATIONAL message TLV Format'>
					<preamble></preamble>
					<artwork align='center'>

 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type (2 octets)         |        Length (2 octets)       | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                     Variable size TLV value                   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

					</artwork>
					<postamble></postamble>
				</figure>
				
				<t>
					TYPE: 2 octet value indicating the TLV type
				</t>
				<t>
					LENGTH: 2 octet value indicating the TLV length in octets
				</t>
				<t>
					VALUE: Variable length value field depending on the type of the TLVs carried.
				</t>
				
				<t> 
					To work around continued BGP churn issues some types of TLVs
					will need to contain a sequence number to correlate a request with
					associated replies. The sequence number will consist of 8 octets
					and will be of the form: (4 octet bgp_router_id) + (local 4 octet number).
					When the local 4 octet number reaches 0xFFF it should restart from
					0x0000. 
					The sequence number is only used if the TLV requires sequencing else it is not included.	
				</t>
				
				<t> 
					The typical application scenario for use of the sequence number is for it to
					be included in a request TLV to be copied into associated reply messages in order
					to correlate requests with their associated replies.
				</t>
			</section>
			
			<section anchor="pri-format" title="PRI Format">
			
				<t> 
					Prefix Reachability Indicators (PRI) are used to represent prefix NLRI and BGP attributes in a request 
					and only prefix NLRI in a response, in this draft. 
				</t>
				<t>
					Each PRI is encoded as a 3-tuple of the form &lt;Flags, Payload Type, Payload&gt; whose fields
					are described below:	
				</t>

				<figure>
					<preamble></preamble>
					<artwork align='center'>
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Flags (1 octet)         |      Payload Type (1 octet)    | 
+---------------------------------------------------------------+
|                     Payload (Variable)                        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
					</artwork>
					<postamble></postamble>
				</figure>

				<t>
					The use and the meaning of these fields are as follows:
				</t>
				
				<t>
					<list style="hanging">
						<t hangText="a) Flags:">
							<vspace />
							Four bits indicating NLRI Reachability:

							<list style="hanging">
								<t hangText="aa) R Bit:">
									<vspace />
									The R (Reachable) bit, if set represents that the prefixes were deemed reachable in the NLRI,
									else represents that the prefixes were deemed unreachable. This bit is meaningless in the context of 
									all currently defined requests and can thus only be found in a response. If found in a request an 
									implementation MUST ignore its state.
								</t>
								<t hangText="ab) I Bit:">
									<vspace />
									The I (Adj-RIB-In) bit, if set in a query, indicates that the requestor wishes for the response to 
									be found in the Adj-RIB-In of the neighbor representing this session, if cleared indicates that
									the Adj-RIB-In of the neighbor representing this session is not searched.
									If set in a response, indicates that the Adj-RIB-In of the neighbor representing this session
									contained this information, if cleared it did not. 
								</t>
								<t hangText="ac) O Bit:">
									<vspace />
									The O (Adj-RIB-Out) bit, if set in a query, indicates that the requestor wishes for the response to 
									be found in the Adj-RIB-Out of the neighbor representing this session, if cleared indicates that
									the Adj-RIB-Out of the neighbor representing this session is not searched.
									If set in a response, indicates that the Adj-RIB-Out of the neighbor representing this session
									contained this information, if cleared it did not.
								</t>
								<t hangText="ad) L Bit:">
									<vspace />
									The L (Loc-RIB) bit, if set in a query, indicates that the requestor wishes for the response to 
									be found in the BGP Loc RIB of the neighbor, if cleared indicates that the Loc-RIB of the neighbor 
									is not searched.
									If set in a response, indicates that the Loc-RIB of the neighbor contained this information, if cleared 
									it did not.
								</t>
							</list>
							The rest of the field is reserved for future use.
						</t>
						<t hangText="b) Payload Type:">
							<vspace />
								This one octet type specifies the type and geometry of the payload.
								<list style="hanging">
									<t hangText="ba) Type 0 - NLRI:">
										<vspace />
										The payload contains (perhaps multiple) NLRI, the format of each NLRI is as defined 
										in the base specification of such NLRI appropriate for the AFI/SAFI.
									</t>
									<t hangText="bb) Type 1 - Next Hop:">
										<vspace />
										The payload contains a Next Hop address, appropriate for the AFI/SAFI. When used 
										in an SSQ (<xref target="simple-state-request"/>) message the response is expected to contain
										prefixes from the selected RIBs which contain this next-hop in their next-hop attribute.
									</t>
									<t hangText="bc) Type 2 - AS Number:">
										<vspace />
										The payload contains a 16 or 32 bit AS number (as defined in <xref target="RFC4893"/>), when
										used in an SSQ message the response is expected to contain prefixes from the selected RIBs 
										which contain this AS number in their AS_PATH or AS4_PATH (as appropriate) attributes.
									</t>
									<t hangText="bc) Type 3 - Standard Community:"> 
										<vspace />
										The payload contains a standard community (as defined in <xref target="RFC1997"/>), when
										used in an SSQ message the response is expected to contain prefixes from the selected RIBs 
										which contain this standard community in their communities attribute.
									</t>
									<t hangText="bd) Type 4 - Extended Community:"> 
										<vspace />
										The payload contains an extended community (as defined in <xref target="RFC4360"/>), when
										used in an SSQ message the response is expected to contain prefixes from the selected RIBs 
										which contain this standard community in their extended communities attribute.
									</t>
									<t hangText="be) Types 5-65535 - Reserved:"> 
										<vspace />
										Types 5-65535 are reserved for future use.
									</t>
								</list>
						</t>	
						<t hangText="c) Payload:">
							<vspace />
								Contains the actual payload, as defined by the payload type, the payload is of variable length, 
								to be calculated from the remaining TLV length.
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
				<t>
					PRI are used for both request and response modes, a response MUST only contain an NLRI (type 0) payload but a request MAY contain
					payloads specifying a type to search for, an implementation MUST validate all PRI it receives in a request against
					the type of request which was made.
				</t>
				<t>
					An implementation MUST NOT send a PRI in response with no NLRI (type 0) payload, this is considered to be invalid.
					If the implementation wishes to signal that a request did not yield a any valid results an implementation
					MAY respond with an NS TLV (<xref target="not-satisfied"/>), using the "Not Found" subcode, for example.
				</t>
									
				</section>
								
			
			
			<section anchor="tlvs" title="BGP OPERATIONAL message TLVs">
				
					
				<section anchor="advise-tlvs" title="ADVISE TLVs">
					<t>
						ADVISE TLVs convey human readable information to be passed, cross boundary to operators, to inform them of past or upcoming
						error conditions, or provide other relevant, in-band operational information.
					</t>
					<section anchor="advisory-demand-message" title="Advisory Demand Message (ADM)">
						
						<t>
							TYPE: 1 - ADM
						</t>
						<t>
							LENGTH: 3 Octets(AFI+SAFI) + Variable value (up to 2K octets)
						</t>
						<t>
							USE: To carry a message, on demand, comprised of a string of UTF-8
							characters (up to 2K octets in size), with no null termination. 
							Upon reception, the string SHOULD be reported to the host's administrator. 
						</t>
						<t>
							Implementations SHOULD provide their users the ability to 
							transmit a free form text message generated by user input.
						</t>
					</section>
					<section anchor="advisory-static-message" title="Advisory Static Message (ASM)">
						<t>
							TYPE: 2 - ASM
						</t>
						<t>
							LENGTH: 3 Octets(AFI+SAFI) + Variable value (up to 2K octets)
						</t>
						<t>
							USE: To carry a message, on demand, comprised of a string of UTF-8
							characters, with no null termination. Upon reception, the 
							string SHOULD be stored in the BGP neighbor statistics field 
							within the router. The string SHOULD be accessible to the operator 
							by executing CLI commands or any other method (local or remote) to 
							obtain BGP neighbor statistics (e.g. NETCONF, SNMP).
						</t>
						<t>
							The expectation is that the last ASM received from a BGP neighbor 
							will be the message visible to the operator (the most current ASM).
						</t>
						<t>
							Implementations SHOULD provide their users the ability to 
							transmit a free form text message generated by user input.
						</t>
					</section>
				</section>
				
				
				<section anchor="state-tlvs" title="STATE TLVs">
					
					<t>
						STATE TLVs reflect, on demand, the internal state of a BGP neighbor as seen from the other neighbor's perspective.
					</t>
					
					<section anchor="reachable-prefix-count-request" title="Reachable Prefix Count Request (RPCQ)">
						<t>
							TYPE: 3 - RPCQ
						</t>
						<t>
							LENGTH: 3 Octets(AFI+SAFI) + Sequence Number
						</t>
						<t>
							USE: Sent to the neighbor to request that an RPCP (<xref target="reachable-prefix-count-reply"/>) message is generated in response.
						</t>
					</section>
					
					<section anchor="reachable-prefix-count-reply" title="Reachable Prefix Count Reply (RPCP)">
						<t>
							TYPE: 4 - RPCP
						</t>
						<t>
							LENGTH: 3 Octets(AFI+SAFI) + Sequence Number +  4 Octet RX Prefix Counter (RXC) + 4 Octet TX Prefix Counter (TXC)
						</t>
						<t>
							USE: Sent in reply to an RPCQ (<xref target="reachable-prefix-count-request"/>) message
							from a neighbor, RXC is populated with the number of reachable prefixes accepted from the peer 
							and TXC with the number of prefixes to be transmitted to the peer for the AFI/SAFI.
						</t>
					</section>
					
					<section anchor="adj-rib-out-count-request" title="Adj-Rib-Out Prefix Count Request (APCQ)">
						<t>
							TYPE: 5 - APCQ
						</t>
						<t>
							LENGTH: 3 Octets(AFI+SAFI) + Sequence Number
						</t>
						<t>
							USE: Sent to the neighbor to request that an APCP (<xref target="adj-rib-out-count-reply"/>) message 
							is generated in response. 
						</t>
						<t>
							APCQ can be used as a simple mechanism when an implementation does not permit or support the use of RPCQ.
						</t>
					</section>
					
					<section anchor="adj-rib-out-count-reply" title="Adj-Rib-Out Prefix Count Reply (APCP)">
						<t>
							TYPE: 6 - APCP
						</t>
						<t>
							LENGTH: 3 Octets(AFI+SAFI) + Sequence Number + 4 Octet TX Prefix Counter (TXC)
						</t>
						<t>
							USE: Sent in reply to an APCQ (<xref target="adj-rib-out-count-request"/>) message
							from a neighbor, TXC is populated with the number of prefixes held in the Adj-Rib-Out for the
							neighbor for the AFI/SAFI. 
						</t>
					</section>
					
					<section anchor="loc-rib-count-request" title="BGP Loc-Rib Prefix Count Request (LPCQ)">
						<t>
							TYPE: 7 - LPCQ
						</t>
						<t>
							LENGTH: 3 Octets(AFI+SAFI) + Sequence Number
						</t>
						<t>
							USE: Sent to the peer to request that an LPCP (<xref target="loc-rib-count-reply"/>) message 
							is generated in response. 
						</t>
					</section>
					
					<section anchor="loc-rib-count-reply" title="BGP Loc-Rib Prefix Count Reply (LPCP)">
						<t>
							TYPE: 8 - LPCP
						</t>
						<t>
							LENGTH: 3 Octets(AFI+SAFI) + Sequence Number + 4 Octet Loc-Rib Counter (LC)
						</t>
						<t>
							USE: Sent in reply to an LPCQ (<xref target="loc-rib-count-request"/>) message
							from a neighbor, LC is populated with the number of prefixes held in the entire Loc-Rib
							for the AFI/SAFI.
						</t>
					</section>
					<section anchor="simple-state-request" title="Simple State Request (SSQ)">
						<t>
							TYPE: 9 - SSQ
						</t>
						<t>
							LENGTH: 3 Octets(AFI+SAFI) + Sequence Number + Single request PRI (Variable)
						</t>
						<t>
							USE: Using a PRI as a request form (See <xref target="pri-format"/>), an implementation
							can be asked to return information about prefixes found in various RIBs.
						</t>
						<t> 
							A single, simple PRI is used in the request, containing a single NLRI or attribute as
							the PRI payload. RIB response filtering may take place through the setting of the 
							I, O and L bits in the PRI Flags field.
						</t>
						<t> 
							An implementation MAY respond to an SSQ TLV in with an SSP (See <xref target="simple-state-response"/>) 
							TLV (containing the appropriate data).
							An implementation MAY also respond to an SSQ with an NS TLV (with the appropriate subcode set) indicating
							why there will not be an SSP TLV in response.
							An implementation MAY also not respond at all (See <xref target="SEC"/>).
						</t>
					</section>
				
				</section>

				<section anchor="dump-tlvs" title="DUMP TLVs">
					
					<t>
						DUMP TLVs provide data in both structured and unstructured formats in response to events, for use in debugging scenarios.
					</t>
					
					<section anchor="dropped-update-prefixes" title="Dropped Update Prefixes (DUP)">
						<t>
							TYPE: 10 - DUP
						</t>
						<t>
							LENGTH: 3 Octets(AFI+SAFI) + Variable number of dropped UPDATE Prefix Reachability 
							Indicators (PRI) (See <xref target="pri-format"/>)
						</t>
						<t>
							USE: To report to a neighbor a structured set of prefix reachability indicators retrievable 
							from the last dropped UPDATE message, sent in response to an UPDATE message which was 
							well formed but not accepted by the neighbor by policy.
						</t>
						<t> 
							For example, an UPDATE which was dropped and the rescued NLRI concerned a number of 
							both reachable and unreachable prefixes, the DUP would encapsulate two PRI, one with 
							the R-Bit (reachable) set, housing the rescued reachable NLRI and the other with the
							R-Bit cleared (unreachable), housing the rescued unreachable NLRI as payload.
						</t>
					</section>
					<section anchor="malformed-update-prefixes" title="Malformed Update Prefixes (MUP)">
						<t>
							TYPE: 11 - MUP
						</t>
						<t>
							LENGTH: 3 Octets(AFI+SAFI) + Variable number of dropped update Prefix Reachability 
							Indicators (PRI) (See <xref target="pri-format"/>) due to UPDATE Malformation.
						</t>
						<t>
							USE: To report to a neighbor a structured set of prefix reachability indicators retrievable 
							from the last UPDATE message dropped through malformation, sent in response to an UPDATE message 
							which was not well formed and not accepted by the neighbor, where a NOTIFICATION message was not sent.
							A MUP TLV may accompany a MUD (<xref target="malformed-update-dump"/>) TLV.
						</t>
						<t> 
							See the example from <xref target="dropped-update-prefixes"/>.
						</t>
					</section>
					<section anchor="malformed-update-dump" title="Malformed Update Dump (MUD)">
						<t>
							TYPE: 12 - MUD
						</t>
						<t>
							LENGTH: 3 Octets(AFI+SAFI) + Variable length representing retrievable malformed update octet stream.
						</t>
						<t>
							USE: To report to a peer a copy of the last UPDATE message dropped through malformation, sent in response 
							to an UPDATE message which was not well formed and not accepted by the neighbor, where a NOTIFICATION message was not sent.
							A MUD TLV may accompany a MUP (<xref target="malformed-update-prefixes"/>) TLV.
						</t>
					</section>
					<section anchor="simple-state-response" title="Simple State Response (SSP)">
						<t>
							TYPE: 13 - SSP
						</t>
						<t>
							LENGTH: 3 Octets(AFI+SAFI) + Sequence Number + Single Response PRI (Variable)
						</t>
						<t>
							USE: Using a PRI as a response form (See <xref target="pri-format"/>), an implementation
							uses the SSP TLV to return a response to an SSQ (See <xref target="simple-state-request"/>) TLV
							which should contain information about prefixes found in various RIBs.
							These RIBs should be walked to extract the information according to local policy.
						</t>
						<t> 
							A single, simple PRI is used in the response, containing multiple NLRI.
							The I, O and L bits in the PRI Flags field should be set indicating which RIBs 
							the prefixes were found in.
						</t>
						<t> 
							An implementation MAY respond to an SSQ TLV in with an SSP TLV (containing the appropriate data).
							An implementation MAY also respond to an SSQ with an NS TLV (with the appropriate subcode set) indicating
							why there will not be an SSP TLV in response. 
							An implementation MAY also not respond at all (See <xref target="SEC"/>).
						</t>
						<t>
							If no data is found to satisfy a query which is permitted to be answered, an implementation MAY respond
							with an NS TLV with the subcode "Not Found" to indicate that no data was found in response to the query.
							An implementation MUST NOT send a PRI in response with no NLRI payload, this is considered to be invalid.
						</t>
					</section>
				</section>
				
				<section anchor="control-tlvs" title="CONTROL TLVs">
					
					
					<t>
						CONTROL TLVs satisfy control mechanism messaging between neighbors, they are used for such functions 
						as to refuse messages and dynamically signal OPERATIONAL capabilities to neighbors during operation. 
					</t>
					
					
					<section anchor="max-permitted" title="Max Permitted (MP)">
						<t>
							TYPE: 65534 - MP
						</t>
						<t>
							LENGTH: 3 Octets(AFI+SAFI) + 2 Octet Value
						</t>
						<t>
							USE: The Max Permitted TLV is used to signal to the neighbor the maximum number of OPERATIONAL messages that will be accepted
							in a second of time (see <xref target="SEC"/>, Security Considerations), an implementation MUST, on receipt of an MP TLV, 
							ensure that it does not exceed the rate specified in the MP TLV for sending OPERATIONAL messages to the neighbor, for the duration 
							of the session.
						</t>
						<t> 
							An implementation MAY send subsequent MP TLVs during the session's lifetime, updating the maximum acceptable rate
						</t>
						<t>
							MP TLVs MAY be rate limited by the receiver as part of OPERATIONAL rate limiting (see <xref target="SEC"/>, Security Considerations).
						</t>
					</section>
					<section anchor="not-satisfied" title="Not Satisfied (NS)">
						<t>
							TYPE: 65535 - NS
						</t>
						<t>
							LENGTH: 3 Octets(AFI+SAFI) + Sequence Number + 2 Octet Error Subcode
						</t>
						<t>
							USE: To respond to a query to indicate that the implementation can or will not answer this query.
							The following subcodes are defined:
						</t>
						<t>
							<list style="hanging">
								<t hangText="0x01 - Request TLV Malformed:">
									Used to signal to the neighbor that the request was malformed and will not be processed. 
									A neighbor on receiving this message MAY re-transmit the request but MUST increment the sequence number.
									Implementations SHOULD ensure that the same request is not retransmitted excessively when
									repeatedly receiving this Error Subcode in response.
								</t>
								<t hangText="0x02 - TLV Unsupported for this neighbor:">
									Used to signal to the neighbor that the request was unsupported and will not be processed. 
									A neighbor on receiving this message MUST NOT retransmit the request for the duration of the session.
								</t>
								<t hangText="0x03 - Max query frequency exceeded:">
									Used to signal to the neighbor that the request has exceeded the rate at which the neighbor finds acceptable
									for the implementation to transmit requests at, see <xref target="max-permitted"/> (MP TLV) 
									and <xref target="SEC"/> and (Security Considerations) for more information.
								</t>
								<t hangText="0x04 - Administratively prohibited:">
									Used to signal to the neighbor that the request was administratively prohibited and will not be processed. 
									A neighbor on receiving this message MUST NOT retransmit the request for the duration of the session.
								</t>
								<t hangText="0x05 - Busy:">
									Used to signal to the neighbor that the request will not be replied to, due to lack of resources estimated
									to satisfy the request. It is suggested that, on receipt of this error subcode a message is logged to inform
									the operator of this failure as opposed to automatically attempting to re-try the previous query. 
								</t>
								<t hangText="0x06 - Not Found:">
									Used to signal to the neighbor that the request would have been replied to but does not contain any data
									(i.e the data was not found).
									An implementation MUST NOT send a PRI response with no NLRI payload, this is considered to be invalid.
								</t>
							</list>
						</t>
						<t>
							NS TLVs MAY be rate limited by the receiver as part of OPERATIONAL rate limiting (see <xref target="SEC"/>, Security Considerations).
						</t>
					</section>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>					
		<section title="On the use of STATE and DUMP TLVs">

		<t>
			The STATE TLVs use three classes of counters, defined in this document: sent counters (TXC), received counters (RXC) and current table state counters (LC).
			The table state counters (for example number of BGP RIB entries) are exchanged only for informational purposes and they should not be subject to comparison with any local counter values.
		</t>
		<t>
			Where a query of the neighbor's RXC is required to be correlated, the local TXC coupled with the sequence number SHOULD be stored and used to perform such a correlation. If a discrepancy is detected, an automated or manual Route Refresh message can be triggered (utilising Start_of_Refresh and End_of_Refresh markers) that would allow for purge of any stalled data across two BGP databases.
		</t>
		<t>
			It is important to note that, as BGP is never stable it is expected that the counters will also be subject to continues value change making any comparison of their values questionable.
		</t>
		<t> The DUMP TLVs report information back to an operator about messages which were not accepted, from machine-readable rescued UPDATE NLRI to an entire copy of the malformed UPDATE message. These can be used for troubleshooting purposes when such a message is transmitted and the implementation gracefully continues (such as treat-as-withdraw).
		</t>
		
			

		</section>
		
		<section title="On the use of ADVISE TLVs">
			<t>
			   The BGP routing protocol is used with external as well as internal
			   neighbors to propagate route advertisements.  In the case of external
			   BGP sessions, there is typically a demarcation of administrative
			   responsibility between the two entities.  While initial configuration
			   and troubleshooting of these sessions is handled via offline means
			   such as email or telephone calls, there is gap when it comes to
			   advising a BGP neighbor of a behaviour that is occurring or will occur
			   momentarily.  There is a need for operators to transmit a message to
			   a BGP neighbor to notify them of a variety of types of messages.
			   These messages typically would include those related to a planned or
			   unplanned maintenance action.  These ADVISE messages could then be
			   interpreted by the remote party and either parsed via logging
			   mechanisms or viewed by a human on the remote end via the CLI.  This
			   capability will improve operator NOC-to-NOC communication by
			   providing a communications medium on an established and trusted BGP
			   session between two autonomous systems.
			</t>

			<t>
			   The reason that this method is preferred for NOC-to-NOC
			   communications is that other offline methods do fail for a variety of
			   reasons.  Emails to NOC aliases ahead of a planned maintenance may
			   have ignored the mail or may have not of recorded it properly within
			   an internal tracking system.  Even if the message was recorded
			   properly, the staff that are on-duty at the time of the maintenance
			   event typically are not the same staff who received the maintenance
			   notice several days prior.  In addition, the staff on duty at the
			   time of the event may not even be able to find the recorded event in
			   their internal tracking systems.  The end result is that during a
			   planned event, some subset of eBGP peers will respond to a session/
			   peer down event with additional communications to the operator who is
			   initiating the maintenance action.  This can be via telephone or via
			   email, but either way, it may result in a sizeable amount of replies
			   inquiring as to why the session is down.  
			</t>
			<t>
			   The result of this is that the NOC responsible for initiating the maintenance 
			   can be inundated with calls/emails from a variety of parties inquiring as to the
			   status of the BGP session.  The NOC initiating the maintenance may
			   have to further inquire with engineering staff (if they are not
			   already aware) to find out the extent of the maintenance and
			   communicate this back to all of the NOCs calling for additional
			   information.  The above scenario outlines what is typical in a
			   planned maintenance event.  In an unplanned maintenance event (the
			   need for and immediate router upgrade/reload), the number of calls
			   and emails will dramatically increase as more parties are unaware of
			   the event.
			</t>
			<t>
			   With the ADVISE TLV set, an operator can transmit an
			   OPERATIONAL message just prior to initiating the maintenance specifying
			   what event will happen, what ticket number this event is associated
			   with and the expected duration of the event.  This message would be
			   received by BGP peers and stored in their logs as well as
			   any monitoring system if they have this capability.  Now, all of the
			   BGP peers have immediate access to the information about this
			   session, why it went down, what ticket number this is being tracked
			   under and how long they should wait before assuming there is an
			   actual problem.  Even smaller networks without the network management
			   capabilities to correlate BGP events and OPERATIONAL messages would
			   typically have an operator login to a router and examine the logs via
			   the CLI.
			 </t>
			 <t> 
				This draft specifies two types of ADVISE TLV, a DEMAND message (ADM)
				and a STATIC message (ASM), it is anticipated that the DEMAND message 
				will be used to send a message, on demand to the BGP neighbor, to inform them
				of realtime events. The STATIC message can be used to provide continual,
				"Sticky" information to the neighbor, such as a contact telephone number or 
				e-mail address should there be a requirement to have continual access
				to this information.
			</t>

		</section>
		
		<section anchor="error-handling" title="Error Handling">
			<t>
				An implementation MUST NOT send an OPERATIONAL message to a neighbor in response to an erroneous or malformed OPERATIONAL message.
				Any erroneous or malformed OPERATIONAL message received SHOULD be logged for the attention of the operator and then MAY be discarded.
			</t>
		</section>
		
		
		<section anchor="SEC" title="Security considerations">
			<t>
				No new security issues are introduced to the BGP protocol by this specification. 
			</t>
			<t>	
				Where a request type is not supported or allowed by an implementation for some reason, the implementation MAY send an 
				NS (<xref target="not-satisfied"/>) TLV in response, the Error subcode of this TLV SHOULD be set according to the reason
				that this request will not be responded to.
			</t>
			<t>
				Implementations MUST rate-limit the rate at which they transmit and receive OPERATIONAL messages. 
				Specifically, an implementation MUST NOT allow the handling of OPERATIONAL messages to negatively
				impact any other functions on a router such as regular BGP message handling or other routing protocols.
			</t>
			<t>
				Although an NS error subcode is provided to indicate that a request was rate-limited, an implementation need not reply to 
				a request at all, this is the suggested course of action when rate-limiting the sending of responses
				to a neighbor.
			</t>
			<t>
				An implementation MAY send an MP (<xref target="max-permitted"/>) TLV to indicate the maximum rate at which it will accept 
				OPERATIONAL messages from a neighbor, upon receipt of this TLV the sender MUST ensure it does not transmit above this rate
				for the duration of the session. 
			</t>
			<t>
				An implementation, considering a request to be too computationally expensive, 
				MAY reply with the "Busy" NS error subcode to indicate such, though the implementation need not reply to the request.
			</t>
			<t> 
				Implementations MUST provide a mechanism for preventing access to information requested by SSR (<xref target="simple-state-request"/>) messages
				for the operator. Implementations SHOULD ensure that responses concerning the Loc-RIB (PRI with L-Bit set or responses which would set the L-Bit)
				are filtered in the default configuration. 
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="IANA Considerations">
			<t>
				IANA is requested to allocate a type code for the OPERATIONAL message from the BGP Message Types registry, as well as requesting a type code for the new OPERATIONAL Message Capability negotiation from BGP Capability Codes registry.
			</t>
			<t>
				This document requests IANA to define and maintain a new registry named: "OPERATIONAL Message Type Values". The allocation policy is on a first come first served basis.
			</t>
			<t>
				This document makes the following assignments for the OPERATIONAL 
				Message Type Values:
		</t>
		
		<t>
			<list style="hanging">
				<t hangText="ADVISE:">
					<vspace />
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Type 1 - Advisory Demand Message (ADM)</t>
						<t>Type 2 - Advisory Static Message (ASM)</t>
					</list>
				</t>
				<t hangText="STATE:">
					<vspace />
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Type 3  - Reachable Prefix Count Request (RPCQ)</t>
						<t>Type 4  - Reachable Prefix Count Response (RPCP)</t>
						<t>Type 5  - Adj-RIB-Out Prefix Count Request (APCQ)</t>
						<t>Type 6  - Adj-RIB-Out Prefix Count Response (APCP)</t>
						<t>Type 7  - Loc-Rib Prefix Count Request (LPCQ)</t>
						<t>Type 8  - Loc-Rib Prefix Count Response (LPCP)</t>
						<t>Type 9  - Simple State Request (SSQ)</t>
					</list>
				</t>
				<t hangText="DUMP:">
					<vspace />
					<list style="symbols">		
						<t>Type 10 - Dropped Update Prefixes (DUP)</t>  
						<t>Type 11 - Malformed Update Prefixes (MUP)</t>
						<t>Type 12 - Malformed Update Dump (MUD)</t>  
						<t>Type 13 - Simple State Response (SSP)</t>
					</list>  
				</t>
				<t hangText="CONTROL:">
					<vspace />
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Type 65534 - Max Permitted (MP)</t>
						<t>Type 65535 - Not Satisfied (NS)</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</list>
		</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="ACK" title="Acknowledgements">
			<t>
			This memo is based on existing works <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-advisory"/> and <xref target="I-D.raszuk-bgp-diagnostic-message"/> which describe a number of operational message types documented here. The authors would like to thank Enke Chen, Bruno Decraene, Alton Lo, Tom Scholl, John Scudder and Richard Steenbergen for their valuable input. 
            </t>
		</section>
	</middle>
	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
			  &RFC1997;
		      &RFC2119;
			  &RFC4271;
			  &RFC4360;
			  &RFC4760;
			  &RFC4893;
		  	  &RFC5492;
		</references>
		<references title="Informative References">
			 &draft-raszuk-bgp-diagnostic-message-02;
			 &draft-ietf-idr-advisory-00;
			 &draft-shakir-idr-ops-reqs-for-bgp-error-handling-01;
			 &draft-retana-bgp-security-state-diagnostic-00;
			 &draft-nalawade-bgp-soft-notify-01;
			 &draft-nalawade-bgp-inform-02;
			 &draft-jasinska-ix-bgp-route-server-02;
		</references>
	</back>
</rfc>
